## **Atul Kumar**

MPhil Scholar, CESP, JNU



+91-82982-95950

## PROFESSIONAL PROFILE

I am a skilled economist with an MPhil in Economics from Jawaharlal Nehru University and a MA in Economics from the Central University of South Bihar. My expertise is in Development Economics, Statistical and Econometric Methods, and Statistical Programming and Reproducible Research. With experience as a Research Officer at the A N Sinha Institute of Social Sciences and Guest Faculty at Miranda House College, DU, I have a passion for Behavioral Economics, Public Policy, and Financial Literacy. I am skilled in R and Latex languages and MS Excel, EViews, and Stata. Having published papers on the impact of COVID-19 on the stock market, exchange rate, and gender-based violence, I am highly motivated with strong academic background and practical experience in research and teaching.

## **EDUCATIONAL QUALIFICATIONS**

## Jawaharlal Nehru University

MPhil in Economics
Dissertation Submitted

New Delhi, India Jan 2021 – Jan 2023

Courses: Methods of Economic Analysis; Development Economics; Statistical and Econometric Methods; Statistical Programming and Reproducible Research

#### **Central University of South Bihar**

MA in Economics

Gaya, Bihar Aug 2018 – May 2020

Percentage: 85.2% (Gold Medallist)

Courses: Microeconomics I & II; Macroeconomics I & II; Mathematical Methods in Economics I & II; Statistical Methods and Applications, Development Economics I & II; Money and Banking; Introductory Econometrics; Financial Economics I, II & III; International Economics; Indian Economic Development; Econometric Methods; Software Applications of Econometrics; Statistical Computing; Environmental Education; Public Finance; Field Survey and Report Writing; Advanced Topics in Applied Econometrics; Environmental Economics

# Patna University BA (Hons) in Economics

Patna, Bihar Aug 2015 – May 2018

Percentage: 67.63%

Courses: Principles of Economics, Mathematical and Statistical, Methods for Economics; Micro and Macro Economics; Economic History of India (1857-1947) and Comparative Economic Development (1850-1950); India's Economic Development since 1947; Development Theory and Experience, Economy; State, Society and Public Economics; Money, Financial Markets and International Economics

## **University Grants Commission**

NET with JRF in Economics

Dec 2019

#### **General Aptitude Test in Engineering (GATE)**

Humanities and Social Sciences

March 2021

## **Work Experience**

#### **Research Officer**

A N Sinha Institute of Social Sciences

Feb 2023 – Mar 2023 Patna, Bihar

In my role as a Research Officer, I successfully contributed to the "Dalit Development Index: Why is Growth and Status among Indian States uneven?" project. My responsibilities encompassed a wide range of tasks, including identifying appropriate villages for the survey, designing effective questionnaires, conducting field research, analysing data, creating comprehensive graphs and charts, conducting literature reviews, and compiling a detailed report of findings.

**Guest Faculty** 

Miranda House College, DU

Mar 2023 – May 2023 *New Delhi* 

In my capacity as a Guest Faculty, I deliver high-quality instruction to undergraduate students in two courses: Introductory Macroeconomics and Financial Literacy. Through my engaging and dynamic teaching methods, I aim to equip students with the knowledge and skills necessary to succeed in these fields.

#### **SKILLS**

- Languages: R, Latex
- Tools: MS Excel, EViews, Stata, Kobo Toolbox

## RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

#### MPhil Dissertation

Title: Evolution of Behavioural Economics and Its Impact on Public Policy in the Global South – A Literature Review

Under the supervision of *Prof Sujoy Chakravarty*, this study undertakes a comprehensive review of literature on the effectiveness of behvaioral economics-induced public policies which are implemented in the global south.

#### Master's Dissertation

Title: Socio-Economic Indicators and Financial Literacy: A State-Level Analysis in India

Under the supervision of Mr. Atish Kr Dash, this study explores the relationship between socioeconomic variables such as savings, borrowings, and income of individuals and their level of financial literacy.

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

- Kumar, A., Nigam, N & Shrivastava, S (2022). Gender-Based Violence and COVID -19: The Indian Scenario. In Sandhya R. Mahapatro (Ed.), *COVID-19 & Socioeconomic Challenges in India: Through the lens of Migration, Health & Gender* (pp 177-194). Bookwell Publication.
- Bhattacharyya, R., Rama, S., Kumar, A., & Banerjee, I. (2021). Dynamic Structural Impact of the COVID-19 Outbreak on the Stock Market and the Exchange Rate: A Cross-country Analysis Among BRICS Nations. arXiv preprint arXiv:2102.05554.
- Banerjee, I., Kumar, A., & Bhattacharyya, R. (2020). Examining the Effect of COVID-19 on Foreign Exchange Rate and Stock Market An Applied Insight into the Variable Effects of Lockdown on Indian Economy. arXiv preprint arXiv:2006.14499.

## **CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS**

- Does Democracy Improve the Quality of Life? A Cross-Country Analysis at the National Conference on Appropriate Technologies for Rural India organised by Chandragupt Institute of Management Patna in association with NABARD.
- Gender-Based Violence and COVID-19: The Indian Scenario at the ICSSR sponsored National Seminar on COVID-19 in India & Sustainable Development Goals: Challenges, Responses & Way forward organised by A N Sinha Institute of Social Studies, Patna.

## WORKING PAPERS

- Impact of Democracy, Region and Income on Human Development: A Cross-Country Analysis A Study
- Assessment of differences in views of the decision-making approaches of Herbert Simon, Kahneman and Tversky
- Evolution of Behavioral Economics A Systematic Literature Review

## PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

- Participated in *Three Days National Workshop on Application of EViews and STATA Packages for the analysis of Socio-Economic Data* from 26th March to 28th March 2019, organised by Dept. of Economic Studies & Policy, Central University of South Bihar, Gaya.
- Participated in *Two Days National Workshop on Big Data Analytics* from 14th March to 15th March 2019, organised by Dept. of Computer Sciences and Economic Studies & Policy, Central University of South Bihar, Gaya.

#### CERTIFICATIONS

- Data Analysis in Public Policy, CPPR Academy, 23<sup>rd</sup> August 2022.
- Academic Writing, SWAYAM, 18th November 2020.
- Advanced Microsoft Excel, Tata Steel, 7<sup>th</sup> June 2020.
- Understanding Open Educational Resources, Commonwealth of Learning, Canada, 31st March 2020.

#### ROLES AND RESPONSIBILITIES

- Placement Representative at the Department of Economic Studies and Policy at CUSB from July 2019 to June 2020.
- Member of the Institutional Innovation Council (IIC) at the Central University of South Bihar from June 2018 to October 2020.

## **EXTRA-CURRICULAR ACTIVITIES**

- Represented Bihar and Patna University in the National Youth Festival 2017 as a student of Patna University.
- Participated in Zonal Rounds of the RBI Policy Challenge in 2019 and 2020.
- Won Regional Rounds of the RBI Policy Challenge in 2019 and 2020.

## REFERENCES

## Prof. Sujoy Chakravarty

Professor of Economics Centre for Economic Studies and Planning, School of Social Sciences, Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi, 110067.

Email: sujoy@jnu.ac.in

Relationship: MPhil Supervisor

## Mr. Atish Kumar Dash

Assistant Professor,
Department for Economic Studies and Policy,
Central University of South Bihar,
Gaya, Bihar.

Email: atish@cub.ac.in

Relationship: Course Instructor

## PERSONAL DETAILS

• Date of Birth: 26th January 1999

• Language Proficiency: English and Hindi

• Interests: Reading, Swimming, Haiku.